<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
  <!-- The spaces between the open and close "a" tag are mandatory.  (Cuz HTML renderers are dumb...) -->
  <a name="intro"> </a>
  <h3>Introduction</h3>
	<p>
    This IG defines the extensions that are globally defined and available in 
    all FHIR implementation contexts. Prior to <a href="http://hl7.org/fhir/R5">R5</a>
    these extensions were defined in the  core specification, but starting from R5
    they have been moved out of the specification into a separate extensions pack
    so that the extensions can be updated more often than the base specification.
    This extension pack also defines some search parameters for the extensions.
  </p>
  <p>
    In addition, the extension pack also contains a series of <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}mapping-language.html">mapping language</a>
    scripts that provide a formal executable definition of the relationship between 
    R5 and the prior versions R4 and R4B. These are located in the extension pack to allow 
    them to also be updated as they are tested and used in production and improvements are made.
  </p>
	<a name="topics"> </a>
	<h3>Content Registries</h3>
	<ul>
    <li><a href="extension-registry.html">Extension Registry</a></li>
    <li><a href="search-params.html">Search Parameters for the Extensions</a></li>
    <li><a href="conversion-registry.html">R5/R4(B) Conversion Registry</a></li>
  </ul>
  
	<a name="policy"> </a>
	<h3>Update Policy</h3>
  
	<a name="policy-extensions"> </a>
	<h4>Extensions</h4>
  
  <p>
  References to the extensions defined in this extension pack are found in <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}extensibility.html#Extension">Extension.url</a> 
  or in profile references to defined extensions in <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}elementdefinition.html#ElementDefinition">ElementDefinition.type.profile</a>.
  While the profile references may be versioned using <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}references.html#canonical">canonical versioned references</a>, 
  the most important references are in <code>Extension.url</code> and these are version-less.
  </p>
  <p>
  For this reason, the extensions defined in this extension pack are managed very conservatively with regard to 
  breaking changes:
  </p>
  <ul>
   <li>Extensions that are active are not subject to breaking changes. New extensions will be introduced if necessary</li>
   <li>Extensions labelled 'draft' may have breaking changes if the FHIR Management Group is satisfied that they are not in 
     use in production, or if all the existing users are agree to making the change. The exact rules and processes still 
     being discussed, but not all 'draft' extensions are subject to change</li>
   <li>In this regard, the definitions for <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}versions.html#change">breaking change to Normative artifacts</a> 
     apply. Note that the focus of these rules is preserving the validity and meaning of existing extensions, not preventing applications 
     processing extensions from having to change</li>
    <li>The extensions all have the status of 'trial-use' but once they are active they are treated as normative. The FHIR
     Management Group has not yet decided how these extensions will be balloted in the future</li>
  </ul>

	<a name="policy-extensions"> </a>
	<h4>Conversion Maps</h4>
  
  <p>
  The implementation scope of the conversion maps is fixed: implementing a proper transform from 
  R4/R4B to R5 and vice versa. Ongoing changes may be made to the maps if they improve the mappings
  within this scope, including catering for common extensions.
  </p>

	<a name="ip"> </a>
	<h3>Intellectual Property Considerations</h3>
	<p>
    This implementation guide and the underlying FHIR specification are licensed as public domain under the <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}license.html#license">FHIR license</a>.  The
    license page also describes rules for the use of the FHIR name and logo.
  </p>
  <p>    
    This guide includes extensions making use of terminologies such
    as LOINC and SNOMED CT that have more restrictive licensing requirements.  Implementers should make themselves familiar with licensing and
    any other constraints of terminologies used as part of their implementation process.  In some cases,
    licensing requirements may limit the systems that data captured using certain codes may be shared with.
  </p>
  {% include ip-statements.xhtml %}
  
<div style="display: none">
  <a name="igs"> </a>
  <h3>Dependencies</h3>
  <p>
    This IG depends on the following additional IGs:
  </p>
  
  {%include dependency-table-short.xhtml %}


  {%include globals-table.xhtml %}
</div>

</div>