<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../input-cache/schemas/R5/fhir-single.xsd">
  <a name="notes"> </a>
  <h3>Additional Notes</h3>
  <ul>
    <li>
      The Library pointed to by this extension could be stand-alone or contained.  If it is specific to a single definition,
      contained is often simpler as it ensures that the rendering algorithm is maintained at the same time the definitional resource
      is, though separate maintenance could make sense if the maintainers of the artifacts will be distinct.
    </li>
    <li>
      The Library <b>SHOULD</b> have a <code>type</code> of 
      <a href="https://terminology.hl7.org/en/CodeSystem-library-type.html#library-type-logic-library">logic-library</a> code to 
      confirm its purpose.  
    </li>
    <li>
      If producing narrative, the resulting content <b>MAY</b> need to be wrapped in a
      <code>&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;...&lt;/div&gt;</code> element before inserting as the text.div value.  
    </li>
  </ul>

  <a name="security"> </a>
  <h3>Security considerations</h3>
  <p>
    There are two classes of risk associated with the use of this extension:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>The risks incurred by executing the code found in the template</li>
    <li>The risks produced by displaying or processing the generated rendering</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    In both cases, the risk can be mitigated but not entirely eliminated.  As a result, it is important that systems using
    this extension have a level of trust in the Library being executed.
  </p>
  <p>
    Details about the risks associated with different languages are covered in the section <a href="#language">below</a>.
    In terms of the generated content, the risks vary.  An obvious risk is that the renderer could generate content that is
    incorrect or misleading.  (This can be a risk even if there is no malicious intent, due to improper design or incomplete testing).  
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li><b>text</b> - This has minimal risk.  It is possible, with the use of complex UTF directional codes to produce text that
      is misleading.  It is also possible to produce text that looks like HTML, which may in turn cause certain consuming systems
      to treat it as such, in which case the risks listed below for unfiltered HTML also apply</li>
    <li><b>FHIR XHTML</b> - FHIR XHTML is XHTML that has been validated to ensure that it complies with the
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}narrative.html#xhtml">FHIR XHTML rules</a>.  This means that no active content is present.
      However, <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}security.html#narrative">some security risks</a> still exist.  Also, FHIR-XHTML is
      only (relatively) safe if the system consuming actually verifies that the XHTML meets the FHIR rules before displaying it.</li>
    <li><b>HTML</b> - In addition to the risks present in the sanitized FHIR XHTML, regular HTML can contain embedded scripts that
      could result in a range of malicious behavior, including exfiltrating data and/or modifying the system rendering the content</li>
    <li><b>PDF and other syntaxes</b> - PDFs, MS Office files, and many other formats carry the risk of malicious behavior.  Even
      if received from a trusted source, running the content through anti-virus software before opening is advisable. </li>
  </ul>

  <a name="output"> </a>
  <p>
  </p>  
  
  <a name="language"> </a>
  <h3>Choosing a language</h3>
  <p>
    This extension puts no constraints on the languages used, however there are a few that serve as good candiates:
  </p>
  <a name="liquid"> </a>
  <h4>Liquid</h4>
  <p>
    HL7 defines a <a href="https://confluence.hl7.org/spaces/FHIR/pages/66938964/FHIR+Liquid+Profile">FHIRPath-aware form of Liquid</a>.
    The base <a href="https://shopify.github.io/liquid">Liquid language</a> is open source and was developed by Shopify as a simple mechanism to help construct 
    static websites (i.e. HTML content).  The <a href="http://hl7.org/fhirpath">FHIRPath</a>-enabled syntax has slight variations that allow embedding 
    FHIRPath expressions as part of the value content, assignments, and conditional and looping expressions.  This allows significant flexibility and
    complexity in creating a rendered version of a resource.  This approach is already used to support producing 
    <a href="https://build.fhir.org/ig/FHIR/ig-guidance/template.html#liquid">generic rules</a> for rendering narrative as part of the HL7 IG publishing tool.
  </p>
  <p>
    This approach has a few benefits:
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>It naturally intermixes HTML and the expressions that drive custom content.  This makes authored content resemble the layout of the page
      the Liquid is describing.</li>
    <li>It is syntax agnostic.  The FHIRPath Liquid engine can consume any FHIR syntax (JSON, XML, RDF, or even in-memory objects).</li>
    <li>It cannot make external calls, making it safe to execute (though the <a href="#security">risks</a> of malicious rendered content
      still hold.</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    The primary drawback is that while there a a number of publicly available Liquid engines, the number of engines that support FHIRPath Liquid is 
    currently quite limited.  It is supported in the HAPI Java reference implementation and there is work underway on a Javascript equivalent.
  </p>

  <a name="xslt"> </a>
  <h4>XSLT</h4>
  <p>
    XSLT has long been used as a language for generating HTML content.  That was one of its original purposes.  There are a wide range of XSLT
    engines available, though most of these are for the limited XSLT 1.0 version, not the more expressive newer versions.  Similar to Liquid,
    the organization of the content can mirror the layout of the target HTML document, making the content easier to interpret and maintain.
    It has a different feature set than Liquid.  In some ways, it XSLT is more sophisticated as it can support recursion and defining custom
    functions.  However, it is missing useful features such as 'markdownify'.
  </p>
  <p>
    The most significant downside of XSLT is that it only funcitons on an XML representation of the resource, which may require serializing
    and re-parsing the instance.  XSLT also has the ability to read data, both locally and from the network, which can create security issues.
    Newer versions and extensions can introduce further security concerns through support for file writing as well.
  </p>

  <a name="cql"> </a>
  <h4>CQL</h4>
  <p>
    <a href="https://cql.hl7.org/">CQL</a> is a language commonly used in FHIR that can manipulate FHIR objects irresepective of what syntax they are
    received in.  It provides full computable expressivity and supports sophisticated navigation of FHIR structures with relatively simple syntax.
    Without leveraging additional modules, native CQL has no ability to access or changes to the local file system, which can reduce security concerns.
    It is widely used in decision support, but it can be used in a variety of contexts.
  </p>
  <p>
    With CQL, the narrative is assembled using string concatenation, often using functions to manage the appropriate wrapping of data in HTML tags or
    whatever other syntax is needed. 
  </p>
  
  <a name="other"> </a>
  <h4>Other languages</h4>
  <p>
    There are a range of other langaguages that could be used.  Languages such as Javascript can have the ability to manipulate file systems, access
    data, and perform a range of other functions.  While sandboxed execution is possible, sharing content in languages like this generally deemed
    to be more prone to security issues because the software capabilities are higher and the behavior of the code can be harder to analyze.
  </p>
  
  
</div>
